Guide to the Rice University Undergraduate Curriculum Committee records, 1964 -2017 UA 236
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Undergraduate Curriculum Committee records
1964-2017
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 236
4 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
The collection consists of records of the work of the faculty Committee on the Undergraduate Curriculum over the period 1966 through 1990. There are membership lists, meeting minutes, reports, memoranda, and correspondence. Topics covered include general graduation requirements, specific requirements in particular departments, evaluation of particular programs, student advising, curriculum revision, and debate about credit for Advanced Placement courses.
Biographical / Historical
The Committee on the Undergraduate Curriculum is one of fifteen committees of the faculty. During the years represented in the records comprising this collection, the members of the committee were appointed by the University president. The committee was made up of eight or nine members, some of whom served for multiple years. The records include committee membership lists.
There were three parts to the charge that determined the committee's work. The primary one was "to review any matter relating to the structure or content of all the undergraduate curricula." These matters could originate in "the University Council, any standing committee of the University, faculty and student groups, members of the administration and others." It was stated that "the Committee will make appropriate recommendations concerning these matters to the University Council and the President."
The second part of the charge was "to initiate, whenever appropriate, reviews of the general curriculum, any of the undergraduate major curricula, distribution requirements and the like, and make recommendations to the University Council and the President."
The third part of the charge was "to prepare a brief, written report on the year's activities of the Committee at the end of the academic year and to submit copies of this report to the President of the University and the University Council."
In years subsequent to the creation of the records in this collection, the University Council has been replaced by the Faculty Senate.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of papers recording the work of the Rice Faculty Committee on the Undergraduate Curriculum. The timespan represented is 1966 through 1990, but not every year in the period is represented, and content varies from year to year.
There are Committee membership lists for the thirteen-year period 1966 to 1979 and meeting minutes for the eleven years 1967 to 1978. These records are also in the forms of reports, memoranda, and correspondence.
Topics covered include general graduation requirements for undergraduate degrees, such as the foreign language requirement, the English competency exam, distribution requirements, and construction of minors. Many particular departments are represented as issues arose concerning requirements involving their specific courses. Debate within the faculty about how Rice should treat presentation by incoming students of Advanced Placement courses is covered. There is information about recommendations for student advising. Results of evaluating particular programs are included, as are records of the major curriculum revision project that culminated in 1970.
Finally, the collection includes response forms from faculty to a survey concerning the number of hours judged appropriate for a Rice degree. The date of this survey is not apparent, but the names of faculty represented suggest that it took place in the sixties.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 1-4 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Boxes 5-8 stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is restricted. Permission to use these papers must be obtained from the Faculty Senate.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the President's Office, Rice University.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges
Document Types
minutes (administrative records); letters (correspondence); notes
- Series I: Committee structure, 1966-1984
  - Membership, 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1967-1978, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Accounting/Principles of Business, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Subject files, 1966-1977
  - Advanced Placement, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Advising, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anthropology and Sociology Dept., 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Architecture, School of, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bachelor of Science Program, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biochemistry, Dept. of, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Charles Freeman Case, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Classics, Dept. of, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - College Courses – SCEP Report, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - College Courses, 1967-1974, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Commerce, Dept. of – Studies and Evaluations, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Commerce, Dept. of – Report of the Committee to Review and Evaluate, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Commerce, Dept. of, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Course Load (Survey of other universities), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Course Load Reduction, 1971-1972; Course Load Reduction Questionnaire, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Curriculum Revision, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Curriculum Revision Proposal, 1970; Reactions, student and faculty, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Curriculum Suggestions, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Requirements, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Distribution Requirements, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Education, Dept. of, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - English Competency (Exam), 1970-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Science and Engineering, Dept. of, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Esso Foundation, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Experimental Program in Composition, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fine Arts Program, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Foreign Language Requirement, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - French, Dept. of, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - German, Dept. of, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Geology, Dept. of, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Health and Physical Education, Dept. of, 1968-1971, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - History, Dept. of, 1966-1970, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Honors Program, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Houston Inter-University African Studies Program, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Human Sexuality, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Interdepartmental Programs/University Major, 1968-1973, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Jan Plan, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Linguistics, Dept. of, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Materials Science, Dept. of, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mathematical Sciences, Dept. of, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Pass – Fail, 1967-1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Religious Studies, Dept. of, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rice-Baylor Medical Program, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rice-Columbia Law Program, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - ROTC, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Russian, Dept. of, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Science – Mathematics Requirement, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Self-Study, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Semester (Credit) Hours, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Separate Curricula, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Shepherd School of Music, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Statistics (Courses), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Tutorial Program, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Undergraduate Minors, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Series III: Committee correspondence and notes, 1964-1990
  - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee, Miscellaneous Reports and Memos, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Memos, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Memos, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Memos, 1967-1968, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Memos, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Memos, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notices, Minutes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Memos, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Memos, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1972 Questionnaire on Course Requirements for Graduation (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Notes, Budgets, Surveys, Proposals, etc., Computer Science Program Committee, 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - [(Sub) Committee for] Science/Engineering Foundation Course, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Notes, [ad hoc] Committee to Review Foundation Courses, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Minutes, proposals, and correspondence, 2006-2007
  - Mission, charge to committee, committee members, historical overview, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2006-06-2007-05 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of other interested groups: Student Assn., Faculty Senate, Alumni board, Deans Council, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Other universities' programs, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Senate meeting, 2007-01-17 (Box 5)
  - Curriculum, Kathy Matthews files -- not vetted, n.d. (Box 5)
  - CUC Data Bill Wilson, n.d. (Box 5)
- Series V: Minutes, proposals, and correspondence, 2008-2017
  - Minutes, proposals and correspondence, 2008-2009 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Minutes, proposals and correspondence, 2013-2014 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, proposals and correspondence, 2014-2015 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - QEP as related to curriculum, 2015 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, proposals and correspondence, 2015 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, proposals and correspondence, 2016 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, proposals and correspondence, 2015-2016 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Working group on General Education and Distribution Requirements, 2017 (Box 8, Folder 3)